music blitz notes

These songs were made with the FE8 drum fix in mind.
If you hear bleepbloop noises on the drum tracks, be sure to use the fix.
https://www.dropbox.com/s/1pj067ddvayr1zq/drumfix_fe8.ups?dl=0
A song list is at the end of this document.


	INTRODUCTION

These songs are made for FE8's native instrument map. I have included the original .mid files so
you may adjust them as needed for your own instrument setup. Keep in mind that the songs use
special effects such as pitch bend and modulation (in small enough amounts that they don't make
the GBA sound engine go crazy), so for the best result please refrain from scrubbing those things
from the songs when you insert them.


	NOTES ON MIDI EDITING

If you wish to edit the midi files included (to put your own twist on them, make them work with different
instruments/samples, etc), you will notice that if you are using Anvil Studio, the app will yammer at you
about "this track has multiple volume changes/pan changes/instrument changes. Would you like to
delete these?" if you try to switch some tracks' volumes/instruments. To avoid this, press "cancel" and
refrain from using Anvil's meters/buttons/etc to make these changes. Instead, go to "View ->Event list"
to look at the event list of the midi. The ProgramChange events are what make the instruments change
mid-track, ChannelVolume controls volume, and Panpot controls L/R panning; you can double-click any
of these events to edit them with a value of 0—127 (so for example, "ProgramChange Chan 3: Value: 80"
changes track 3's instrument to №80 (lead: square). Directly editing the midi's event list is somewhat
of an esoteric solution to accessing features that Anvil tries to lock behind a paywall, but it gives you
full control of your music.

Additionally, "Edit ->Insert midi event..." will let you insert one of these events yourself at whatever
point in the song the cursor is. I recommend setting "insert midi event" to Ctrl+D as a useful hotkey
in Anvil's settings. Some other hotkey suggestions: Ctrl+L for "view note properties"; Ctrl+B for "paste
and mix" (as opposed to paste and insert; this mirrors how Ctrl+V and Ctrl+B differ in a hex editor);
Ctrl+N for "paste special" (lets you paste just the notes without the special control events attached,
or vice versa); Ctrl+P to insert a program change; Ctrl+S to save (the default hotkey for Ctrl+S in Anvil
begins a recording— I can't tell how you many times I accidentally did that before I changed the key combination).

When altering modulation (applies a "wahwah" effect to a note), be careful. While midi synths on PCs
usually interpret modulation in terms of addition, the GBA sound engine interprets it in terms of multiplication,
meaning anything above 5 or so is going to sound terrible (unless it is being intentionally used to make the
note sound very distorted). This is why an innocuous, unaltered midi might "warble" when you insert it
in a GBA rom: it has huge amounts of modulation slapped onto it, which sounds good on a computer but
terrible on the GBA. This is no reason to be afraid of modulation: used effectively, it can create a variety
of effects such as a quivering high string note or a groovy, twangy-sounding bass. ipatix's midfix4agb app
is very useful to use to scale down the modulation in a song so it caps at something reasonable like 8
instead of 127.

xoxo
—Аlusq


	SONG LIST
	(I don't know the actual names of all the songs, but this should be enough to know what the song is)


filename		song title		original game			suggested uses

ar-cassandra		Cassandra		Act Raiser			cutscenes: subdued victory; peaceful towns; "everything was okay after all"
ar-fillmore		Fillmore		Act Raiser			player phase: adventurous-sounding
ar2-deception		Deception (Lovaous)	Act Raiser 2			cutscenes: shocking revelations; the protagonist is defeated; the main villain reveals himself
cv2-dwell		Dwelling of Doom	Castlevania 2: Simon's Quest	boss fight (tier 2)
fe2-boss		Boss			FE2				boss fight (tier 1)
fe3-offtowarremix	Off to War (remix)	FE3				boss fight (tier 2)
fe12-endless		Endless Struggle	FE12				player phase: rigourous journey; starts out unsure-sounding before becoming more resolute
lang2-egbert		Egbert			Der Langrisser			enemy phase
ps4-motaviantowns	Town (Motavia)		Phantasy Star 4			cutscenes: tranquillity; relief; gentle smiles
ps4-organicbeat		Organic Beat		Phantasy Star 4			player/enemy phase or cutscene? might be cool to use for both phases at once in a shorter/more cinematic chapter
solbrain-boss		Boss			Shatterhand			boss fight (tier 1 or 2)
trs-knightsoflazeria	Knights of Lazeria	Tear Ring Saga: Heroes of Ytna	player phase: heroic-sounding

